<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Robin Wilson's books and reading journal, and other projects</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 23:24:32 +1100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 23:24:32 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thomas Gold - Taking the Back off the Watch</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thomas Gold&lt;/b&gt; 2012. &lt;em&gt;Taking the Back off the Watch. A Personal Memoir&lt;/em&gt;.  Heidelberg: Springer. 232 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are (at least) two ways to think about the process and problem of trying to advance a new theory in a field where a  different theory is established. One is to treat the phenomenon as social and cultural, as done most famously (&lt;em&gt;The Structure of Scientific Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;) by the philosophers &lt;strong&gt;Thomas Kuhn&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Imre Lakatos&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Paul Feyerarbend&lt;/strong&gt; and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way is to read accounts of scientists who have first hand experience.  &lt;strong&gt;Galileo&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Alfred Wegener&lt;/strong&gt; would be two famous examples.  But the career of &lt;strong&gt;Thomas Gold&lt;/strong&gt;, as related first hand in this compelling autobiography, surely has no equal in terms ofa single researcher having such seminal impact in so many different fields. Physiology and medicine, radar, radio astronomy, cosmology, geology …  It is especially evident that in each case his progress was based on a fundamental understanding of the natural laws and properties of materials relevant to the problem.  Equally clear is that the established workers in the field whose ideas were shown to be ill informed lacked that understanding and the knowledge to apply it.  Eg the ear…  eg ultrasound in medicine… eg the sudden onset of magnetic storms due to solar radiation.   In each case Tommy explains his ideas as “simple”, which they are, but only to one with his level of basic understanding.  Hence, very often it was other physicists who he could rely on to debate his ideas rather than specialists in some scientific discipline.  And the list of those physicists is salutory: &lt;strong&gt;Einstein&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Bondi&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Heisenberg&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Hoyle&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Feynman&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Freeman Dyson&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Lawrence Bragg&lt;/strong&gt; among many others.  Reinforcing earlier impressions from other biographies, even among these fabled theorists, Tommy rated &lt;strong&gt;Feynman&lt;/strong&gt; top (“12 out of 10” on his personal intellect scale). &lt;strong&gt;Feynman&lt;/strong&gt; is also the only one Google’s spell checker seems to know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone bookmarking interesting topics in this book will find themselves bookmarking nearly every page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women are almost completely absent from the narrative, and from the group photos from 1940s working life at Cambridge, and in more recent groups.  A sign of the times, and an indication that the proportion of women in science has increased significantly, if not to anywhere near equality. Despite the subtitle ‘a personal memoir’, personal matters are omitted too; Tommy lets his hair down in chapter 5, where he lets us know that by 1952, at age 32, he has a wife and daughter.  Neither had rated a mention earlier!  Later on, photographs reveal the existence of Tommy’s second wife &lt;strong&gt;Carrie Gold&lt;/strong&gt; and that he had four daughters. Tommy’s era was a time when privacy was respected and “a personal memoir” meant something rather different than it does in 2016.  The short postscript by &lt;strong&gt;Carrie Gold&lt;/strong&gt;, however, does provide a brief balance to the objective main narrative, and reveals something of his relationships with family and golden retriever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/physics%20and%20mathematics/history%20and%20pre-history/2016/08/02/taking-the-back-off-the-watch.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/physics%20and%20mathematics/history%20and%20pre-history/2016/08/02/taking-the-back-off-the-watch.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>physics and mathematics</category>
        
        <category>history and pre-history</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>P.W. Singer &amp; August Cole - Ghost Fleet</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;P.W. Singer &amp;amp; August Cole&lt;/b&gt; 2015. &lt;em&gt;Ghost Fleet&lt;/em&gt;.  Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 416 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another somehwat plausible near-future disaster scenario.  A bit of a page-turner, albeit highly predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time China making war on — not a nearby soft target — but the US. Pearl Harbour revisited, if you please.   Easy to tell this is written by a couple of Washington defense analysts (they declare this is fiction, not prediction, but one wonders).  Other ingredients include Chinese takeover of the digital environment thanks to hacked Chinese microchips now almost ubiquitous in the latest US military hardware; revival of analogue military hardware (the “Ghost Fleet”) and some retired personnel; a Hawaiian guerrilla force fighting the occupying forces; Russia a largely passive ally of China; US-sponsored privateer retaking the space station.  The rest of the NATO world barely exists in this US-centric tale, beyond passing mention of the UK and Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likely to be taken up by Hollywood with Clint Eastwood and Tommy Lee Jones trotted out yet again.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/07/02/ghost-fleet.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/07/02/ghost-fleet.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fiction</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>James Bradley - Clade</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;James Bradley&lt;/b&gt; 2015. &lt;em&gt;Clade&lt;/em&gt;.  Australia: Penguin. 239 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dysfunctional personal relationships, increasingly  severe climate change disasters on a global scale, illnesses and deaths first among main characters then as global epidemic, deaths of species, refugee movement from ecological disasters on vast scales, near collapse of human civilisation.  Readers who delight in these things and such all-to-believable near future scenarios should dive right in.  Only in the last 20 pages do some traces of hard sf, and hope, intrude.  You have been warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of all, not imaginative enough to consider satisfying sf. Its very plausibility - no original ideas, everything here is already in the mind of many a conservationist - is the downfall of this well written novel.  Not a bad book, if you like that sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/06/28/clade.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/06/28/clade.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fiction</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Michael Harris - Mathematics Without Apologies</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Michael Harris&lt;/b&gt; 2015. &lt;em&gt;Mathematics Without Apologies. Portrait of a problematic profession&lt;/em&gt;.  Princeton: Princeton University Press. 438 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is rare to find a book with no redeeming features, but this is one.  A fatuous, self-indulgent, undisciplined, unstructured and uninformative stream of conciousness from a professor of mathematics whose students are to be pitied.  Or rescued.  After a hundred pages of pointless drivel, and a skim through some random later pages, I gladly gave up.  Even the extensive list of references had barely 5 items I felt worth reading.  Four I already own.  There are plenty of warning signs I should have been alert to before purchase: The chapter “How I Acquired Charisma”. The first sentence of the Preface: “When this book was nearly done and my colleagues started asking me what it is about, I found it simplest to answer that it’s about how hard it is to write a book about mathematics.”  The repeated chapters revisiting the theme “How to explain number theory at a dinner party”.  The absence of any notable modern mathematician or mathematics commentator among the promotional blurbs.  A more accurate title would have been  &lt;em&gt;Self-portrait of a problematic mathematician (apologies: no mathematics within).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that, whether or not he is aware of it, &lt;strong&gt;Michael Harris&lt;/strong&gt; had a readership of one in mind: himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would give the book away but there is no-one I think so poorly of.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/physics%20and%20mathematics/2016/06/21/mathematics-without-apologies.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/physics%20and%20mathematics/2016/06/21/mathematics-without-apologies.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>physics and mathematics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steven Pinker - The Sense of Style</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Steven Pinker&lt;/b&gt; 2015. &lt;em&gt;The Sense of Style. The thinking person’s guide to writing in the 21st century&lt;/em&gt;.  London: Allen Lane. 359 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the title, not a style guide, but certainly a guide to writing.  Much to be learned here.  Henceforth to live on my desk, along with  &lt;em&gt;Fowler’s Modern English Usage&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Stephen Murray-Smith&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;em&gt;Right Words&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Huddleston&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;Pullum&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;em&gt;A Student’s Introduction to English Grammar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haven’t read it all, more of a reference (as the author himself advises).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not without faults.  I found Chapter 4 &lt;em&gt;The web, the tree, and the string&lt;/em&gt; totally impenetrable (a damning criticism of a book which claims to be a guide to clarity in writing).  I couldn’t come to grips with the extensive use of branching tree diagrams to explain relationships between grammatical elements in sentences.  Perhaps it was me; I might try again one day.  I could have done with some guidance on hyphenation (“sea-level” or “sea level”?  “saltwater”, “salt-water” or “salt water”?).  But &lt;em&gt;hyphen&lt;/em&gt; does not even appear in the index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights so far include the valuable advice, well and truly taken on board, not to over-use pointers: “this is what the previous paragraph was about” and “this is what the next paragraph is about” or even “this is what this paragraph is about”.  Instead, just say it! Also the timely criticism of the increasingly widespread and very irritating incorrect use of apostrophes, often with ludicrous results.    And his advice not to get hung up about split infinitives, lest one write nonsense such as “I’m moving to France not to get fat”.  There are numerous other examples of how not to write (a rich field, admittedly) which makes for highly amusing reading. I daresay &lt;strong&gt;Stephen Pinker&lt;/strong&gt; (should he read this paragraph) would (if he could be bothered) advise me not to over-do parentheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 6 &lt;em&gt;Telling right from wrong. How to make sense of the rules of correct grammar, word choice, and punctuation&lt;/em&gt; is the most valuable.  It is full of instructions on correct usage, examples of incorrect usage, and explanations.  To be consulted regularly.  If only it could be made compulsory reading for serial offenders such as sports commentators and authors or retail signs and newsletters.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/writing/2016/06/15/the-sense-of-style.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/writing/2016/06/15/the-sense-of-style.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Don DeLillo - Zero K</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Don DeLillo&lt;/b&gt; 2016. &lt;em&gt;Zero K&lt;/em&gt;.  London: Picador. 274 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protagonist, listless Manhattan son Jeffrey, his wealthy tycoon father Ross, and his stepmother Anita (archaeologist, now terminally ill), revolve around one another in slightly dysfunctional relationships that however become warmer (or anyway less remote) as first Anita, then Ross, gravitate towards cryogenic preservation.  The cryogenic facility is in Chelyabinsk where a dystopian architectural vision has been realised in order to prepare the patients for a life that is eternal, but evidently post-human.  Or perhaps sub-human.  The facility has been built thanks to Ross’ vast wealth.   While in the vat, awaiting medical and scientific advances that will allow cures and re-animation, the patients retain a whisker of conciousness thanks to pharmacology and nanotechnology which are unspecified; &lt;strong&gt;DeLillo&lt;/strong&gt; has no need of such menial matters. Son Jeffrey rejects the offer of this eternal (but unproven) future, although it is only with the last words of the novel that &lt;strong&gt;DeLillo&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to finally and fully declare his humanist hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the themes are dying and not dying, father and son, mother and son. This could be considered as near future science fiction, except that the science is hardly there at all and the fiction is so sparely written that there is hardly enough of it to classify.  Is it fiction or barely concealed non-fiction drawn from some present-day cryogenic facility in California?  If only &lt;strong&gt;DeLillo&lt;/strong&gt; would write hard science fiction with more of a narrative, the philosophical questions and humanist declarations,  when they came, would hit harder. &lt;strong&gt;Iain M. Banks&lt;/strong&gt; comes to mind.  Instead it is in off the deep end, and you had better be ready to swim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DeLillo&lt;/strong&gt; clearly demands respect, or what passes for it, from critics.  And so, most of the published reviews I’ve read are pretentious, even though the reviewers have not noticed that the novel certainly is not.  It is just a sparsely-written sketch of a future where not one of the choices is inviting, and where the worst options are places no-one would enter willingly.  Probably I should read something written by &lt;strong&gt;DeLillo&lt;/strong&gt; when he was younger.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/06/07/zero-k.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/06/07/zero-k.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fiction</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hannah Kent - Burial Rites</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hannah Kent&lt;/b&gt; 2013. &lt;em&gt;Burial Rites&lt;/em&gt;.  Sydney: Picador. 338 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although based on actual historical events and people, this is still very much a novel.  On the face of it, &lt;strong&gt;Agnes Magnúsdóttir&lt;/strong&gt;, co-accused of murder of two men, is the principal character whose story is slowly revealed.  However in my mind the harsh Iceland of the 1800s and Icelanders themselves overwhelmingly leave the most lasting impression.   In that spirit, a few observations on Iceland and Icelanders of the era are appropriate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nearly all Icelanders have been literate since about 1800 (as &lt;b&gt;Hannah Kent&lt;/b&gt; tells us in closing). By comparison, in Great Britain at about the same time 53% of the population was literate &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/literacy/&quot;&gt;according to Max Roser&lt;/a&gt;. (I haven’t found historical statistics for Australia.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The final execution in Iceland was in 1830, the execution that is the subject of this novel. Capital punishment was abolished for most offences in Iceland in 1869 and abolished completely in 1928.  In Australia the final execution took place in 1967 (accompanied by wide public outrage that ensured final repeal). Infamously, parts of the USA still think it is a good idea.  And we won’t even talk about Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The events related in this book take place soon after the eruption of the volcano Laki in 1783, which resulted in the death of 80% of livestock and starvation of 25% of the human population.  Iceland itself is of relatively recent origin (20 milliion years) and the population has suffered frequent natural disasters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to seek out discussions of if, and if so how, the harsh environment might have promoted progressive social attitudes in Icelanders sooner than in many peoples elsewhere.  Another time…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the novel. &lt;strong&gt;Hannah Kent&lt;/strong&gt;’s sympathetic portrayal of &lt;strong&gt;Agnes Magnúsdóttir&lt;/strong&gt; as a victim of injustice is not universally shared so the historical evidence must be lacking. (Evidently modern Icelanders still relate to the events of the novel, which have been the subject of film and of other books.  Perhaps a moment in history where the culture of popular opinion and historical facts collide, akin to &lt;strong&gt;Ned Kelly&lt;/strong&gt; in Australia?)  This novel is an account of Agnes that is convincing and plausible, but not necessarily accurate (as &lt;strong&gt;Hannah Kent&lt;/strong&gt; admits in her Author’s Notes, pp. 333-335). I  would warm to the novel more if the portrayal of Agnes was supported by historical evidence.  But then it is a novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Burial Rites&lt;/em&gt; could be interpreted as a celebration of relationships and how they build even (especially?) in the most adverse circumstances.  As, for example, between Agnes and the rural family who house her between her conviction and execution.  And as between Agnes and &lt;strong&gt;Natan Ketilsson&lt;/strong&gt;, her lover and alleged murder victim.  But the depiction of life in 1800s Iceland is vivid, detailed and convincing (and evidently based on much historical research by the author), so much so that Iceland itself emerges strongly as a character in the novel.  And to me, the dominant one.  I read &lt;em&gt;Burial Rites&lt;/em&gt; as a celebration of how humans have not only survived in the most adverse environments and circumstances, but, in many parts of the world, managed to also build increasingly progressive societies with many morally sound characteristics.  Despite regular backwards steps, the overall trend so far seems clear (see &lt;strong&gt;Steven Pinker&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Better Angels of our Nature&lt;/em&gt;; link to come).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kate, whose copy of &lt;em&gt;Burial Rites&lt;/em&gt; I read, also pointed me towards these splendid complementary recordings of the &lt;em&gt;Sagas&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Richard Fidler&lt;/strong&gt; in conversation with &lt;strong&gt;Kari Gislason&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/earshot/features/saga-land/&quot;&gt;ABC Radio National&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/05/24/burial-rites.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/fiction/2016/05/24/burial-rites.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fiction</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nick Bostrom - Superintelligence</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nick Bostrom&lt;/b&gt; 2014. &lt;em&gt;Superintelligence. Paths, Dangers, Strategies&lt;/em&gt;.  Oxford: Oxford University Press. 328 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ambitious book about a topic normally reserved for science fiction writers: Is it plausible that artificial intelligence (AI) could one day exceed human capabilities? What would be the consequences?  What should we do about it?   No doubt many would consider such questions should remain within the realm of science fiction. Not so long ago similar voices no doubt would have said the same about nuclear weapons, satellites, antibiotics, transplant surgery, humans walking the surface of the moon, the internet (the what?), smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly these are serious questions worth asking (a view shared by the likes of &lt;strong&gt;Bill Gates&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Max Tegmark&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Martin Rees&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/strong&gt;).  &lt;strong&gt;Bostrom&lt;/strong&gt;’s method is to think hard about the likely steps along the way, make cogent arguments about the issues and reach the most plausible conclusions.  The result is a book where each of these steps forms a (usually) short, easily digested chapter, notwithstanding the doltish comment from &lt;strong&gt;Tom Chivers&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;em&gt;The Telegraph&lt;/em&gt; who classifies himself thus by asserting the book to be “a damned hard read”.  It isn’t, although the final chapters do become longer as more complex material is discussed. However, skimming over some of the detail could be done without missing the main message.  For the reader in a hurrry, this strategy is assisted by the very short overview of the content to come at the startof each chapter.  Summary tables of key points within many chapters are helpful also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bostrom&lt;/strong&gt; has provided extensive endnotes and an impressively eclectic bibliography, so much so that nearly every page threatens a potentially long diversion into multiple parallel reading threads. It is no criticism of the preceding text to say that the bibliography is almost the best part of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1 is a short, thorough and very readable survey of the technical history up to now of AI development. Chapter 2, similarly charts likely future paths.  Subsequent chapters discuss different forms that superintelligent AI might take (speed superintelligence, collective superintelligence, quality superintelligence) then proceed to discuss the timing and speed of a future intelligence explosion.  These early chapters gradually accumulate the impression that although clearly deeply considered, nevertheless what is presented here are opinions, some better supported than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 6 contemplates likely abilities that a superintelligent AI might possess.  Chapter 7 speculates on what goals a a superintelligent AI might have.  Would the outcome of takeover by a superintelligent AI inevitably be doom for humans (chapter 8)?   How could we control it (chapter 9)?  If several superintelligent AIs were to be created simultaneously, what would likely happen (chapter 11)?  And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 14 asks the reader to think about the strategic directions — what long-term science, technology policy decisions should we take, and how to apply these questions to the issue of superintelligent AI?  For example, is it feasible to limit or prevent development of a dangerous technology by witholding research funds? Is it safer for several groups or nations to develop AI collaboratively? (Yes.)  Chapter 15 more briefly and bluntly asks “What is to be done?”. At risk of ruining the suspense, &lt;strong&gt;Bostrom&lt;/strong&gt;’s answer: “Will the best of human nature please stand up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one were to strive to be critical, most chapters don’t arrive at a clear conclusion.  But then, could anyone, on questions such as these? At least &lt;strong&gt;Bostrom&lt;/strong&gt; is honest about it.  And he provides a valuable counterpoint to more rosy view of an AI-led future, such as &lt;strong&gt;Ray Kurzweil&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://timeteam.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/How-to-create-a-mind&quot;&gt;How to create a mind&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/mind%20and%20artificial%20intelligence/2016/05/11/superintelligence.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/mind%20and%20artificial%20intelligence/2016/05/11/superintelligence.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mind and artificial intelligence</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fredrik Sjöberg - The Fly Trap</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fredrik Sjöberg&lt;/b&gt; 2006. &lt;em&gt;The Fly Trap&lt;/em&gt;.  New York: Pantheon Books. 278 pp. Translated from the Swedish by Thomas Teal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first this seems merely a harmless ramble on the subjects of collecting, hoverflies, life on a small Swedish island and &lt;strong&gt;René Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; (inventor of the Malaise trap for catching insects, famous only among entomologists).  (&lt;strong&gt;René Malaise&lt;/strong&gt;, 1892–1978, was a previous inhabitant of the island of Runmarö, where the author &lt;strong&gt;Sjöberg&lt;/strong&gt; now lives.)  A modest amount of autobiographical content is also dispersed through the narrative.  The “collecting” content and commentary is inconsequential due to the arbitrary and narrow interest of the author who declares early on that he is only interested in the hoverfly family and only in those species that can be found on his own island.  It would, however, have been a big mistake to abandon reading this book (as I nearly did).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently this little book is has the status of a minor cult book in the author’s native Sweden. I was not at first similarly impressed, but it grew and grew.  Partly because &lt;strong&gt;Sjöberg&lt;/strong&gt;’s knowledge of hoverflies and other insects is much greater than he initially makes out, but also because of the depth of his historical research into the life of &lt;strong&gt;René Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; who was an adventurous traveller. He spent nearly the entire 1920s decade in Kamchatka and Japan in very difficult  conditions then followed up with a trip to remote parts of Burma (although with a new wife).  Another adventure was planned to Ceylon, India and the Himalaya but abandoned due to the Second World War.  As &lt;strong&gt;Sjöberg&lt;/strong&gt; points out, such adventurers have long since been replaced by filmmakers, although &lt;strong&gt;Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; and his like had an equivalent role and great public recognition in their day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On another level, the author gradually leads the reader to believe that this is just a book about slowing down, about gaining pleasure from making, without haste, observations of the natural world.  Whatever.  Hardly a novel or controversial view to advocate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, when I was almost ready for a second time to abandon the book, yet again an unexpected reward for persistence:  in Chapter 14 it is revealed that &lt;strong&gt;René Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; rejected the theory of plate tectonics, which was only recently becoming widely accepted.  Although he also held some loopy ideas about Atlantis and other things, &lt;strong&gt;Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; wasn’t totally wrong about everything (who is?).  Some quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;Sjöberg&lt;/strong&gt;’s words (p. 205):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Wegener’s theory was humbug.  The earth’s  crust, he insisted, was far too thick.  No force on earth could be strong enough to propel such a sideways migration.  Never.  He found particularly ridiculous the piece of the theory that said the Indian subcontinent had come whizzing along from the south with such force that the collision with the rest of Asia had pushed up the Himalayas and the Tibetan plateau.  Not a chance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Malaise&lt;/strong&gt; in his own words (p. 213):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Scientists of to-day, be it geologists, geophysicists, or oceanographers, are so overspecialized that they master only a limited sector of their own branch.  Outside this sector they hardly dare to express an opinion.  The fundamental theories on which, for instance, geology is based have mostly been in use for generations and have in their mind ceased to be theories and have attained almost the standing of axioms.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sjöberg&lt;/strong&gt; again (p. 216):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When everything is said and done, the days of really revolutionary breakthroughs are perhaps not over.  Maybe, sooner or later, someone will sweep Wegener right out of the door.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more to come on that, elsewhere.  For the moment, and in the spirit of even-handedness, one advocate of the most plausible alternative to plate tectonics &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.expansiontectonics.com/index1.html&quot;&gt;is here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.skepticblog.org/2009/11/23/no-growing-earth-but-a-growing-problem-with-science-journalism/&quot;&gt;the web abounds with many shrill responses from plate tectonics advocates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/natural%20history/2016/04/02/The-Fly-Trap.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/natural%20history/2016/04/02/The-Fly-Trap.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>natural history</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lee Smolin - Time Reborn</title>
        <description>&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lee Smolin&lt;/b&gt; 2013. &lt;em&gt;Time Reborn. From the crisis of physics to the future of the Universe&lt;/em&gt;. London: Allen Lane. 319 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book &lt;strong&gt;Lee Smolin&lt;/strong&gt; makes the case that, contrary to the views of &lt;strong&gt;Einstein&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Leibniz&lt;/strong&gt; , time is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a relative quantity in a universe where both space and time are distorted by gravity.  Instead, &lt;strong&gt;Smolin&lt;/strong&gt; claims that time is the only fundamental property of the universe and that everything else (space, gravity, and the forces described by &lt;strong&gt;Newton&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Einstein&lt;/strong&gt; and quantum mechanics) are emergent properties of an as-yet undiscovered universal physical law.   He claims that apart from time, everything else that surrounds us, and that we think we are familiar with, is in some way illusory.   The flow of moments that make up our perception of time, in contrast, is fundamental  to understanding reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stating time to be the only constant, and real, feature of the universe is hardly radical for most readers of this book (though it will be to most modern physicists).  The experience all &lt;strong&gt;Smolin&lt;/strong&gt;’s readers (even the physicists) have of their existence is that time is indeed real.  Older readers especially so.  To read a book proclaiming the obvious is unlikely to be front-page news for most readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Preface, &lt;strong&gt;Smolin&lt;/strong&gt; puts forward the following hypotheses that are developed from his main thesis, that time is the only fundamental property of reality:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever is real in our universe is real in a moment of time, which is one of a succession of moments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The past was real but is no longer real.  We can, however, interpret and analyse the past, because we find evidence of past processes in the present.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The future does not yet exist and is therefore open.  We can reasonably infer some predictions, but we cannot predict the future completely.  Indeed, the future can produce phenomena that are genuinely novel, in the sense that no knowledge of the past could have anticipated them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nothing transcends time, not even the laws of nature.  Laws are not timeless.  Like everything else, they are features of the present, and they can evolve over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smolin seeks a theory without initial conditions and one that is independent of background conditions, and he thus seeks a fundamental theory that is internally consistent and does not require imagining the, and from which Newtonian and quantum physics emerge as approximations to his undiscovered.  (But, by positing time as the only constant in nature, this seems to make time the ultimate background condition?!  If &lt;strong&gt;Smolin&lt;/strong&gt; explains in the book why this is not so, then I missed it.)  If I understand &lt;strong&gt;Smolin&lt;/strong&gt; correctly, &lt;strong&gt;Einstein&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Leibniz&lt;/strong&gt;, and most modern cosmologists do “physics in a box”, that is they imagine a system and propose laws aiming to explain how it might work “from the outside”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, at least for me, the central underlying question implicit, but unstated, in this book is “Is it possible, in principle, to understand a system from the inside?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see myself returning to this having read some recent contrary views, especially &lt;strong&gt;Sean Carroll&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;em&gt;From Here to Eternity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/physics%20and%20mathematics/2016/02/25/Time-Reborn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/physics%20and%20mathematics/2016/02/25/Time-Reborn.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>physics and mathematics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
